welcome all the fellowship applicat I'm
SE one of the adult I fellows and just
go
through slides here no
disclosures the title of my talk
isim we have a 46y old male with history
of right atrial pseudo aneurysm rupture
that underwent repair it had
pericarditis with a pericardial Fusion
who's now presenting with recurrent
chest pain and
heada so two months prior to this
admission this patient was hospitalized
with chest pain and low braid fevers he
was found to have a pseudo aneurysm
protruding from the right atrium in
paric carditis and underwent Bine patch
repair or cultures of the pseudo
aneurysm were negative cytopathology of
the paracardial fluid showed some mixed
inflammatory cells with numerous
eosinophils reactive mesothelial cells
histiocytes and
pyes he was discharged after this repair
and hospitalization with ID and
Rheumatology followup for further work
up of what could have been causing this
um he was being worked up in the
outpatient study and then he went to
Israel 10 days ago and while he was
there developed some word finding
difficulty and was noticed by his wife
to have an unsteady date uh he's
returning from this trip now with
worsening left-sided chest pain headache
and
NAA in terms of his past medical history
um he had this atrial pseudo aneurysm
also had a herni repair in the past it's
the medications that he's on no
allergies he lives in Maryland um his
occupation is he sells furniture and he
travels a lot for he's traveled to
Malaysia China and Vietnam in the last
two years to visit factories he's been
both in rural and urban settings he
traveled to Cancun six months ago for
vacation I he keeps a pretty strict
Kosher diet um he has a prior smoking
history he enjoys fishing catch and
release only uh he has a pet dog uh his
brother owns some exotic birds and a pet
lizard and his daughter likes to ride
horses uh he is monogamous with his
wife when we see him um his vitals are
within normal limits he's a Feb s while
room air he's just very uncomfortable
appearing very nauseous um kind of in
the process of
having some emesis he uh is uh Conjuring
TAA are clear his heart sounds normal
lung some normal AB is fairly benign um
his neur oxium there's nothing focal on
his nerves and
rashes in terms of his labs labs are
fairly unremarkable he doesn't have a
lucco yosis he's a little bit anemic um
he does have a slight elevation his
percent of eosinophil on his diff um and
then his BMP is fairly
unremarkable his Imaging those he under
go a CT chest abam and pelv with
contrast and now there are multiple
bilateral solid pulmonary nodules with
surrounding Halo these are new from two
months ago when he was seen he has a
prominent subsidary left cardiophrenic
angle lymph node and prominent right
higher node he has numerous soft tissue
masses in the parac
cardium and then ated subcentimeter
scerotic osus fosi in the left femur and
in the bilateral iliac
bones he's also found to have multiple
enhancing lesions in the temporal lobe
left anterior Thalamus right parial lobe
with paranal Hemorrhage and surrounding
vasogenic EMA lesions shown
here so we have a 46y old male with a
issue of right atrial cism underw
rupture and repair paric carditis
paracardial Fusion is's presenting with
recurrent chest ping to to have new
pulmonary nodules and cerebral
lesions appreciate help with the
differential diagnosis right
right oops oh stop sharing interesting
um situation here in a person that seems
to be relatively healthy and and over
what time frame uh were these symptoms
again I mean two months ago he had the
surgery two month ago he had the surgery
and he felt he recuperated or not yeah
he had some like low fevers after that
then had recovered traveled to Israel
had the workf finding difficulty and the
gate imbalance then returned and then
just a few days ago developed this acute
onset nausea and chest pain yeah yeah so
uh interesting and uh I I'd say a fairly
complicated case uh potentially but uh
oh oh manaw left the room okay all right
so so uh um okay I'm going to move on
from there a little bit um let's see
here um Eileen Scully are you available
to give us some initial thoughts on this
interesting
presentation sorry about that
sure thank
you had trouble unmuting as we all say
um so this is a 46 year old with an
extensive travel history and a
prior unclear
ideology um pseudoaneurysm which had
some inflammatory features for which it
sounds like there was an open infectious
versus inflammatory differential who's
now representing with progression that
we could either link or split but seems
likely related to the initial pathology
with sort of multifocal involvement um
with both CNS disease and pulmonary
nodules and also Seth you did say there
was multiple paracardial soft tissue
lesions as well is that correct yeah
yeah he has some leion yeah masses and
his paric cardium as well and then some
sportic fosi and his femur and his iliac
bones okay so widely
disseminated process um so I'm going to
just be upfront that I have absolutely
zero idea what this is but I will um try
to formulate some possible
possibilities so that we can do some
Diagnostics and then other people can
chime in I think as far just starting at
the beginning it seems unusual for a
standard bacterial process based on the
lack of initial perence or other
features and then the tempo of the
illness with the delay between the
initial repair and then
progression um I think some unusual more
standard bacterial types of organisms
that have more indolent courses like no
cardia can probably not avoid saying
with a pulmonary and CNS
presentation um it could also be the a
more occult bacterial infection with
brain abscesses from embolization and
and Pulmonary abses from the same so I
would put standard bacterial causes
there maybe I don't know something with
the lower virulence like anoxi or um one
of the nutrition nutritionally deficient
strep species but um and I suppose you
always have to say just standard staff
and strap although this just seems very
um
unlikely I think much more plausible
seems to be something like an atypical
process which on which I would include
microbacterial
infection um again with the multi-stem
involvement uh relatively occult to
diagnose is kind of a process although I
don't think of that as being associated
with pseudoaneurysms alth I wish mon was
here to correct me on on that um as also
um I don't know and maybe at least is
here is if there's a particular NTM that
has a vascular predilection um so then
other less common bacterial processes
would they be like um the uh birkhold
area mosis type of presentation with his
travel to Southeast Asia and other
locations where that's
endemic um and then another a typical
bacterial um associated with vascular
presentation would be syphilis although
having a really hard time um imagining
how that's related to the CNS and lung
lesions moving on from that uh fungal
pathogens I think um cidio micosis is
occasionally associated with
pericarditis um it sounds like he's got
sort of Plenty Of Travel such that
histoplasmosis and other things he's
probably been in mic areas crypticus
certainly can cause cryptococcomas and
CNS presentations um with this degree of
dissemination and an IMO compromised
host seems unlikely but I'll I'll leave
it up there and then I have no idea if
blast micosis could do this but I guess
I will just add it to the
list um other processes like parasitic
infections or or things of that nature
um I am having a hard time coming up
with one that would fit that um I mean
in my patients I always think of
toxoplasmosis which can cause both
pulmonary and CNS processes but I just
can't necessarily put that together here
um I'm sure there are other things I'm
leaving out there but I'll leave that
for someone else to fill in and then
viral ideologies um I I'm GNA leave that
one blank um because I I just can't put
one together but maybe someone else can
so I think uh because I'm just fling in
the dark I'll stop and let someone join
me thank you this is truly a strange
case and thanks for starting off with
some really uh important considerations
um anyone from the audience I I was U
sort of wondering so there was bone
there was
pericardial um there was brain and how
many brain uh lesions um at least three
yeah and with the bone I mean I was
thinking of some of the histiocytosis
syndromes which are usually more kids
what's that they just put the same yeah
you know there's all sorts of names
there um you know
leam H sugar schw or something that I've
since forgotten but the whole range of
those kind of macropod syndromes and I
was also just wondering about an immuno
deficiency state that would allow for
something like an NTM to have
dissemination we've seen
anti2
antibodies gamma interferon defects and
so on so some kind of
anti2 or gamma defect that might somehow
lead to a
predilection on that b but U and uh is
his background uh is he ashpazi you know
or I don't yeah I don't know
that FMF can call
serositis um you can get some tissue um
and odd presentation so I just wondering
a little bit about
that osis is that yes I'm add a couple
so um so M Matthew h is added the K
caucus Dave
igg4 yeah this would go under NTM but
Bill just specifically guess the cular
surgery yeah Mar theosis
iosis there's oh an IGG or yeah disease
like a pseudo tumor kind yeah so adding
atino okay and
asilis and then eth is going to add
salmonella pudus
hello hello hello Seth how are we doing
up here not up there not up
there we add bruella
okay okay I'm sorry yes I was saying the
brosis okay it sounds like the well is
dry is it up there now still not up
there all right this is our first stump
of the academic this is you stumped the
CHS all of us so but thanks this is a
tough one for sure I assume saying Rus
but I'm just gonna say I also know okay
I I uh I think this is where tissue is
the issue
right
so but highly interesting presentation
thank you uh Eileen for taking us
through this for being the first
chump no we're all
Chumps perplexed by this and there were
a lot of lot of teams involved
so in terms of infectious workouts we
underwent a BAL with lung biopsy the
lung biopsy just showed alveolated lung
parena with focal organizing pneumonia
bacterial fungal and AFB cultures had no
growth they did a gene expert that was
negative also did an OM on his which was
negative CSF was clear there were no
white blood cells the glucose and the
protein were unremarkable and the CSF
work was negative as well the crypto
bacterial fungal AFB VL H6 JC virus VB
HSV were all negative in terms of his
blood and serology work up negative
t-spot his fungle markers were all
negative uh checked a lot of different
things like Q fever toxo stry HIV Bella
blasto coxy brella and then we even sent
out a carias Next Generation sequencing
on him which was negative as
well so he underwent IR biopsy one of
the paracardial lymph
no you time to have angio
saroma so thinking about this case and
there was a lot of he had been seen in
the outpatient sending by ID there had
been a lot of ID involvement I think
there was a lot of push for ID to come
up with a unifying differential
diagnosis but thinking about this case
one of the things that I wanted to kind
of learn from this and think more about
what are what infections are mimickers
of malignancy and then what malignancy
can mimic infection so in terms of
thinking about mimic I this is just
funny if you H Med search the great
mimer there's over 2,000 articles
ranging from people talking about
malignancy to covid-19 to the EKG being
the great mimickers I think it's just
funny that we use this terminology a lot
that's very uh nons specific but in
terms of the great infectious mimickers
uh I broke this down kind of looking
through the literature and doing a
literature review to see what organisms
most comic most commonly are mimickers
for malignancy um and so these ones I'm
going to call the great infectious
mimickers I think
microbacteria being at the top of this
list um you know really suspicious for
you know findings that can look like
metastatic disease pulmonary malignancy
for example there was a cohort study out
of Japan where there were 16 out of 460
patients who were initially diagnosed
with pulmonary malignancy or later were
diagnosed with microbacteria Bal fungal
infections I think we all have a lot of
respect for um in terms of looking like
metastatic disease as well this was an
interesting cohort study out of Stanford
where they had 12 patients who had
invasive molds who actually were
initially diagnosed with non- small cell
lung cancer um so fungal infections
being involved syphilis I think it was
ozler who called syphilis the great
imitator um and I think it's something
we think less about now but I think can
look like a lot of different types of
malignancy R from rectal cancer to
cutaneous malignancy or metastatic
disease this isn't citation of an
interesting case report where secondary
syphilis mimicked a lympo proliferate
disorder lymphoma the pet scan for is
really remarkable and it looks like the
patient has but actually had second par
syphilis brosis talk a little bit about
I think was interesting in this case for
me at least with the travel to Israel
and then CNS uh manifestations bone
manifestations and you know looking like
potentially paracardial marment
metastatic disease there's an
interesting case report of a patient
from Peru had neuro brosis that mimiced
a CNS tumor that was initially
misdiagnosed
and then bul bold area or mosis
something that we had talked about on
the differential also you know depending
on exposur to something that can look
like metastatic disease or in the case
report bronchogenic
carcinoma for brucelosis I thought this
was interesting was something that was
on my differential when I saw him given
the Bony lesions the neurologic lesions
and the paracardial involvement in the
travel Israel there have been outbreaks
of brosis in Israel and this was
something that I was working on with um
Peter re at the University of Washington
and the center for one Health there so
there have been some outbreaks of
brucelosis there and then this
interesting case report of neurosis that
I was mentioning as well but this
patient had a really strict Kosher diet
and his brosis serology was
unremarkable then the Lesser known
mimics I'm going to call these I think
are ones that are also important to
think about but don't come up in the
literature quite as often bonella being
on this list U mimicking different solid
tumors like breast cancer lymphoma and
saroma there's an interesting um cohort
say I'll talk a little bit about where
there 11 cases of MD Anderson that
initially had all been diagnosed as
cancer um but then came back and they
were actually
bonella um Helman infections um so uh
also can look like metastatic disease I
was really interested in this patient
about Paragon amasis given his travel to
Southeast Asia there's an interesting
case report of pulmonary paragonimiasis
mimicking a metastatic pulmonary tumor
as well as mimicking an
saroma um and so with his cardiac
pulmonary and CNS involvement thought
that parag was interesting and we had
the OM on the B that was negative no
cardia and
actinomyces um which was also on the
differential again things that can be
kind of indolence and mimic metastatic
disease and this is this interesting
case report about three cases of
pulmonary nocardia with cerebral abses
that lung
cancer so in terms of of Bartonella um I
think the history does Bella had a
particular fondness for was the first
organism that I studied um I see with
San Falon Lucy Tomkins and they share
with me kind of their discovery of
bartella as the agent for Basel
angiomatosis so we know bartella can
Celli can cause a Gran this lym fattis
so cat scratch disease or the vascular
proliferation billar angiomatosis that
we see in IMO compromised patients
initially they thought maybe it was AET
seal organism this was kind of you know
in the early days of DNA and sequencing
things like that that they were then
able to identify it um as spens Al as a
bacteria um but it can mimic lots of
different um malignancies and this is
this interesting case um short study um
cohort study from MD Anderson they
looked at 11 cases um who were initially
been diagnosed with malignancy who
actually had cat scratch disease it was
interesting just kind of looking at the
demographics and exposures to cats um in
this cboard and then part of this thing
there's a literature review they look at
36 other cases where cat scratch disease
mimicked malignancy um and the kind of
overall similarities between these cases
is that a lot of them mimics lymphoma as
well as solid tumors in complely press
saroma and skin cancer um so it's kind
an interesting study to look at in open
form infectious
disease and then given this um case I
was also curious about what infections
does angio sarcoma make I think it was
something that um it was unexpected and
I think important to think about going
forward as we try to expand our
differential so angio saroma I Comm make
lots of different infections there's an
interesting case report of a of Ang M
infected aneurysm and pseudo aneurysm um
in the abdominal aorta angio saroma
mimicking cellulitis so people who
initially were diagnosed with cellulitis
of the scalp and facial cellulitis
actually end up having contous
angiosarcoma angara menum paric carditis
kind of like an our patient they had a
primary right atrium angio sacoma
similar to this patient mimicking
pericarditis and then an interesting
case report of angos sacoma mimicking
syphilis this was P SAR that was
initially misdiagnosed as syphilis so I
think just interesting things to keep in
mind um going forward thinking about our
differential so key points from this
case uh I think you can we could think
about the great infectious disease
mimers and malignancy I think micob
bacteria fungal infection syphus forell
Anda my review would be the ones I would
put on here the Lesser known mimickers I
would include martinal helmouth
infections and no cardan
Nyes and I think one of the big learning
points from this case I think there were
some delays in diagnosis and treatment I
think this was initially had been kind
of misdiagnosed as a unknown infection
or rheumatologic sort of disease um
which led to delay ultimate diagnosis
and treatment and that angio saroma can
mimic multiple different
diseases these are the references
here great that was a nice overview I
think Charlotte just made a comment
saying noting LGB can mimic recal cancer
and uh with
HIV as an example of bacteria
mimicking so Seth I mean given the
bindings often the radi ologists help uh
was there clinical correlation suggested
or were some of the nodules more
suggested malignancy or they're like
could be infectious could be malignancy
more of like could be infectious
malignancy um and it was really a lot of
coordination with International real
there was a great International realy so
we were able to get uh sample that note
and there was really it was actually
really remarkable we were talking like
late into the night so we got the path
back and he was talking that you the
diagnosis was made but uh took some and
they don't know where the primary is so
he suspect cardiac so so his prognosis
is not very
good
yeah any uh any questions did he get
empiric antibiotics uh during this or
was yeah that was held off as diagnostic
workout was
yeah was he on the medicine service or
he yes the Giants
okay what is it right right what did
Kelly uh Kelly just saying huge shout
out to the team obtain the specimens
made sure that they all into the labs
appropriately amazing team efforts yeah
often in these complex cases it really
is good communication and coordination
is important I we've filed a number of
um things when things you know you've
asked for things but they don't get sent
and of course it's a surgical sample so
to go back is a big deal so it's good to
have that all on board ahead of time
any other comments um and I think your
points about looking at it from both
ways uh are really important I think at
least for our patient what we get seen
the most is the lump um and where you
know lump tumors and smokers are removed
because of a positive pet scan turns out
to be
Mai something of that nature and that's
probably the number one mimic or
actinomycosis is pretty rare than all
the others I think as you said are war
in the case report territory
so hi stth this is zene um thanks for
that case and also for um I think one of
the things we most of us love so much
about IDE is that we always stay even if
it doesn't look like it's our problem um
I wonder about the use of pet in these
cases not just to look for avidity but
to look for intensity and I know that in
some time case settings that is useful
with like known
malignancies but I don't know how good
we're getting at differentiating whether
something looks like an indolent
infection versus an aggressive
malignancy just because these syndromes
are so hard and here obviously there was
some accessible tissue and that really
helped but in cases where there's not I
do still think we need tools to try and
sort out infection versus things like
malignancy hey well thanks I that's a
that's a great Point any other
comments the ACs is happy that no one
here got it
either well angio sarcomas are a
notoriously difficult tumor because they
will not I mean a lot of times they'll
have Regional spread in a limb but if
they're occurring elsewhere can be very
difficult to to diagnose and I guess in
retrospect the thought was somehow that
process was part of the pseudo ISM but
just wasn't pathologically identified
yeah yeah rapidly Progressive right
right yeah unfortunately some of them
are treatment's really terrible and it's
usually radiation yeah that's what he's
scheduled for
yeah okay well thanks very much I look
forward to meeting um a few uh of our
interviewees today I hope you have a
great day here virtually in Baltimore
and at John's Hopkins and thank you all
for coming in person so until next
Tuesday